It feels like 2024 all over again
because Bellingham is back to BEING THAT
GUY.
>> [screaming]
>> HE'S DRAGGING ENGLAND FORWARD ONCE again
in a major tournament.
>> It's a relief, isn't it?
>> Oh god, yeah. Thank god we've got that
fellow.
>> The ultimate big game player.
>> Harry Kane's your most important player
and I said, "No, I disagree." I said
Jude Bellingham's the one. [music]
Jude's the catalyst.
>> It's 2-1 England. Bellingham's there
once again.
>> Thankfully we've got Jude Bellingham
again. That special something that.
>> From the very first match, Bellingham
set the tone. He scored in England's 4-2
win over Croatia while also becoming the
youngest European player ever to appear
in four major international tournaments.
Then he scored versus Panama.
>> SAKA'S DELIVERY, OH splendid [screaming]
first time [cheering] take
from Jude Bellingham.
>> In the knockout rounds, against co-host
Mexico at the legendary Estadio Azteca,
Bellingham delivered one of the
performances of the tournament. He
scored twice in just 98 seconds,
producing the third fastest brace in
World Cup history. And then came Norway.
England were in trouble against one of
the tournament's surprising stories, but
once again, Bellingham answered the
call. Whenever England have needed
someone to rescue them, Jude somehow
finds a way. But what makes Bellingham's
tournament so special is that on top of
the goals, he's doing everything else,
too. He had a goal-saving clearance
versus Mexico. He's tracking back,
pressing from the front. Under Thomas
Tuchel, he's been given the freedom to
roam all over the pitch. One minute he's
making a crunching tackle, the next he's
gliding past a defender like a winger.
Then moments later, he's arriving in the
box to finish like an elite poacher. He
plays with the confidence and composure
of someone who's been on this stage for
a decade. We all forgot about this
version of Bellingham because we haven't
seen it for two years, ever since Mbappé
joined Real Madrid. When the turtle
arrived, the first player who had to be
sacrificed was Jude Bellingham.
>> Being maybe one of the main guys going
forward, now he had to settle for
something a little bit different this
season.
>> In an effort to get the best out of the
Frenchman, Jude was pushed back to a
deeper role in midfield. What's funny is
that if I told you a few years ago that
Bellingham would be underutilized as a
central midfielder, you would have
laughed in my face. Because throughout
his career, that's where he had been
mainly played. At Birmingham, initially,
he started out wide. Reportedly, he was
played there to help him settle in. But
soon, it was obvious that he was far
more impactful in the middle of the
park.
>> The way I like this, he weren't afraid
to leave his foot in and and [music]
going for the tackle with me and and
stuff like that. And I think just that
mentality
for a young young lad, and I really like
that. I said that straight after the
game, actually. And
>> He wore the number 22 on his back. Not
because it was available, but because it
meant something. Jude wanted to be a
complete midfielder. I'm not making this
up, by the way. That's in his own words.
He picked that number because he didn't
want to be stuck to a certain role. He
didn't just want to be a number six who
defended or a number 10. He wanted to be
a player who could do everything. Track
back, make tackles, carry the ball
forward. But he wasn't the goals and
assists machine we are seeing now. Now,
of course, it's hard to get goal
contributions when you're playing on a
team that's just trying to avoid
relegation. He did get four goals in 45
games.
>> Here's Bellingham in his issue MOMENT IN
FLIGHT.
>> [screaming]
>> OH, WHAT A MOMENT FOR
JUDE BELLINGHAM.
>> AND HE EVEN SET UP A late equalizer
against Charlton Athletic.
>> Well, yeah, it's no surprise that this
has come from a bit of Jude Bellingham
magic. I think
>> It was obvious though that he was
something special. Hence why Birmingham
did something almost unheard of and
retired his number 22 shirt.
>> A young player, he was only 17 going
away. So, it's a ridiculous decision.
>> People laughed at the gesture when it
happened, but who's laughing now? In
July of 2020, his fairytale at
Birmingham came to an end. Borussia
Dortmund came calling, paying 25 million
pounds to sign him. A record fee for
someone that age. It was a massive step
up, but Jude wasn't there to just wait
and learn. He was ready to play and
immediately helped out the black and
yellow. Right from his first game in the
German Cup, he made an impact. He scored
on his debut, becoming Dortmund's
youngest ever goal scorer in a
competitive match. It was a perfect
start. What really stood out was how he
played. He wasn't used as a flashy
number 10 or a defensive midfielder.
Instead, he was playing as an eight, a
box-to-box midfielder right in the heart
of everything. As a midfielder,
Bellingham ran the game. One moment he
was winning tackles deep in his own
half, the next he was bursting forward
to create chances at the other. His work
rate was crazy. He would cover every
blade of grass. At the time, Dortmund
had a revolving door of managers. They
went through managers the way
Bellingham's girl goes through athletes.
But, no matter who was in charge,
Bellingham was always a regular starter.
Even as a teenager, their midfield
looked better when he was in it. His
energy, composure, and aggression made
him stand out. And that was very obvious
when Bellingham scored a brilliant goal
against Manchester City in the Champions
League quarterfinal. He was only 17 at
the time, but he just looked like he
belonged on the biggest stage. That same
season, he helped Dortmund win the
DFB-Pokal, lifting his first major
trophy. And as the years went on, his
influence only grew. He wasn't some sort
of work rate merchant. He did so much
more than that. He wanted the ball at
his feet. He was controlling games. At
times, he was even wearing the captain's
armband.
>> I'm the first English teenager to
captain a team in the Champions League.
What does that mean? How much did you
enjoy the role?
>> Yeah, I think it comes, you know, quite
naturally, [music] to be honest.
>> That's crazy to think about. A teenage
kid captaining a club like Borussia
Dortmund. And it wasn't like he was some
sort of guy that just came through the
academy. He was a foreigner that had
come from England to Germany. In the
2023 season, Bellingham's stats actually
went up again.
>> Erling Haaland, Silas Jude Bellingham!
>> [screaming]
>> A YOUNG MAN WHO, GAME BY GAME, gets
better and better.
>> Even though he was playing strictly as a
box-to-box central midfielder. He wasn't
playing as a false nine, he wasn't a
holding midfielder, he wasn't even a
number 10 at this point. He scored 14
goals and got seven assists and played
practically every single minute. Sadly
though, his efforts weren't enough to
help Dortmund win the Bundesliga.
Despite it being a tight title race for
once in Germany, Dortmund crumbled as
per usual and Jude couldn't do anything
because he was watching from the
sidelines as he was injured. How often
Dortmund choke in the Bundesliga really
needs to be studied. But even with that
heartbreak, Bellingham had done more
than enough to prove his quality. At
just 19, he was voted the Bundesliga
player of the season. He also won the
Golden Boy award in 2023. Bellingham had
become the full package. Pause. He could
put in a strong tackle, but he was calm
on the ball. He was also fearless going
forward, whether he was scoring it
himself or creating for other. A true
box-to-box engine. The biggest clubs in
the world were watching and one of them
made their move. And that was Real
Madrid.
>> Huge breaking story. [music]
The next destination in Jude
Bellingham's career appears to now be
>> [music]
>> decided. Okay, and we have some more
breaking news. Real Madrid have signed
Jude Bellingham. It is confirmed it's a
four-year deal.
>> Just like that, the boy who left
Birmingham for Dortmund was on his way
to the biggest stage of all. At Madrid,
something changed. Under Carlo
Ancelotti, the eyebrow man, Jude was no
longer asked to play as a traditional
box-to-box midfielder like he had done
at Birmingham and Dortmund. Instead, he
was given a new role, a free-roaming
attacking midfielder, a mix between a
false nine and a number 10. It was
risky, but Ancelotti believed that Jude
had all the traits required to be good
in that position. It was the same
position and role that he had used Kaká
in in his Milan sides in the mid to late
2000s. And he was right. Bellingham
exploded out of the gates. In his first
13 matches for Madrid, he scored 13
goals. Two more goals and he would have
gone Benzema's favorite number. These
were ridiculous stats for a midfielder,
especially one new to Spanish football.
>> Yeah, I don't think anyone here really
expected him to come in and be the sort
of leader of this team.
>> Since Madrid didn't have a striker,
Bellingham was the one who stepped up
and became the main man. People wanted
to downplay his goals to it tap-ins. But
number one, the goals looked easy
because his positioning was immaculate.
He was able to get into the right spaces
and pop up at the right time. And then,
of course, he was very clinical in front
of goal. His last-minute winner in his
very first home game at the Bernabeu
sent fans into a frenzy. In a time where
people spent 100 mil on players and they
flop, Bellingham was showing what a
big-money move is supposed to get you,
world-class quality, someone that can
make a difference.
>> And I think that the system, and this is
why you have to give a lot of credit to
managers, the system that Ancelotti put
for him, 4-3-1-2,
he answered the call.
>> And that was proven in El Clasico. In
October of 2023, Madrid were losing to
Barcelona. Then Bellingham, he took
over. First, he blasted a screamer from
25 yards into the top corner. It's a
great finish, but can I criticize Ter
Stegen? Then later in stoppage time, he
sneaks into the box to score again. A
Clasico-winning brace on your debut?
That's the stuff of legends. He had
helped complete the comeback. Playing in
this new attacking role gave Bellingham
the room to show off his full game. He
wasn't just stuck deep in midfield
anymore. He was combining with Vini,
creating chances, and scoring goals.
Yet, he didn't forget the dirty work. He
still dropped back when needed, helping
his team defensively.
>> He do well with the team also off the
ball. People don't often see that. Also,
when he needs to fight, he needs to make
tackles, he's he's also there. And what
most surprised me about him
>> By the end of the season, he had scored
over 20 goals in all competitions. He
had helped Madrid win the double,
Champions League and La Liga. In fact,
in La Liga, he was Real Madrid's best
player. He was carrying the team on his
back, especially when Vini was injured.
He made the Ballon d'Or podium, won the
Kopa Trophy, becoming the first
Englishman to actually ever win that
award. People were now mentioning him in
the same breath as Zidane. Maybe that's
why Bellingham started to tuck in his
shirt. Or maybe he saw Rodri win the
Ballon d'Or with a tucked-in shirt and
thought it'll add to his PR. It wasn't
just hype, though. He was actually
earning it on the pitch. At one point,
he had a better goal-scoring return in a
debut season than Cristiano Ronaldo. He
was scoring so many clutch goals that
you couldn't just say he's getting
lucky. In just one year, Bellingham had
gone from a talented teenager to an
actual global superstar.
>> For me, he's one of the two best players
in
>> [music]
>> in this season in in Europe.
>> He's so good, you know, like
>> started at Birmingham, built up his
dream, goes to Germany, and then you go
to the glorified in Real Madrid. [music]
>> When you play Real Madrid
and you do this
>> He's like he can do everything,
absolutely everything.
And they're only they're very unique
players.
>> He is [music] the future of the football
club, and I think they're in really good
hands. He has everything as a young
midfielder.
>> How can a midfielder
be capable to do all those things with
strikers normally do?
>> He is a superstar. [music] He's going to
be an incredible talent in years to
come.
>> He is a very, very special player.
>> Football, however, is always evolving,
and so did Bellingham's role at Real
Madrid come the new season. Mbappé came,
Kroos left, and Ancelotti decided to
adjust the team. If you guys remember,
Madrid started the season transitioning
into a 4-3-3 with Mbappé as a striker
and Bellingham as a deeper central
midfielder. A very different system than
the 4-4-2 diamond that Madrid used to
win the double the season before. In the
diamond, Bellingham was essentially a
mix between a false nine and a center
attacking midfielder. If we look at his
heat map, he was everywhere, but his
main asset was to be in and around the
box. That's where he was getting the
majority of his goals. Since Madrid
didn't have a traditional nine, there
was plenty of space for the Englishman
to attack. And then on both sides of him
were wingers that could create for him.
If anyone tries to tell you that
Bellingham is just a box crasher or a
tap-in merchant, just know that they
watch football through reels. Cuz yes,
he did camp in and around the box a lot,
but he also scored a ton of goals from
outside the box. He scored a bunch of
goals just going on wonderful solo runs.
He was like the English Gullit doing
everything because he had the complete
freedom and space. He could do whatever
he liked in the attacking third, and the
stats reflected that. But with Mbappé
are occupying the central forward spot
and Vini trying to do too much on the
left wing, Jude's been basically pushed
to the left-hand side of midfield, way
deeper than before. He has to start his
runs all the way from the back, cuz he
has to ensure that the team stays
balanced. You want to see how much extra
work Bellingham has to do now? Look at
Madrid's Champions League loss to Milan.
>> Bellingham trying to make the run,
>> [music]
>> trying to make the team play, running in
behind. As uh that's him again trying to
break the line. That's your nine.
That's
your 10. Again, who's going to make the
run in behind? Who's going to try to go?
>> [music]
>> It's him. It's Bellingham going, not
your number nine.
>> Mbappe up top was not making the runs
that he was supposed to make, which
forced Bellingham, who was playing far
deeper than Mbappe, to make the runs
that he should have been making as the
striker. If Madrid lose the ball, it's
pretty much always Bellingham sprinting
back to stop the counterattacks,
especially given that Mr. 10 times more
and Mr. Sometimes I'm too competitive
don't want to track back.
>> I think sometime in the life I'm too
competitive.
>> At times Bellingham is just shoehorned
into the left mid spot when Madrid are
out of possession, just so that
Ancelotti can try and get the best out
of Vini and Mbappe. The changes in
tactics start to show not just on the
pitch, but on the way that people were
now talking about Jude Bellingham.
That's always been the focus. Since
Mbappe is their new shiny toy, they're
willing to sacrifice anyone and everyone
to get the best out of him. In the first
season at Madrid he couldn't stop
scoring. Literally every single week was
just Bellingham doing this bird
celebration. Game after game you would
hear Bellingham, Bellingham. To this day
it's still one of the best debut seasons
I've ever seen. But fast forward and
things look very different. The goals
have slowed down. He isn't the one
grabbing headlines. Now the spotlight
was on Kylian Mbappe. The guy who loves
the Lakers and LeBron James.
>> Who's your favorite NBA player?
>> LeBron James.
>> Who's your favorite team?
>> Lakers.
>> Who do you think is going to win the NBA
finals next season?
>> Of course I'm going to say the Lakers.
>> The French superstar joined the team and
naturally all the cameras and praise
follow him. Mbappé is getting the
headlines. He's scoring the goal.
Meanwhile, Jude is working harder than
ever and getting half the recognition.
Not to the average fan, it might seem
like Bellingham has faded. And this
makes sense cuz a lot of the people that
praise Bellingham don't actually watch
games. They praised him when he scored
and ignored all the other great things
he did. So now that the goals have dried
up, they think he's not the main story
anymore. But that couldn't be further
from the truth. Jude is still as
important as ever, maybe even more so
because now he's doing the unseen work.
At one point, Bellingham led all Real
Madrid players in duels won, tackles
made, and high-intensity pressure. These
stats are not the ones that are going to
get people an erection. It's not going
to get people excited, but it's some of
the most important statistics to be a
part of. It means he's working hard and
diligently without the ball. When he was
given the freedom to play in the
position that he was so good in in 2024,
Bellingham was still amazing. He popped
out with goals against City and Atalanta
in the Champions League. In late
November and December, he scored in six
consecutive games in La Liga. So he
wasn't slowing down. In fact, he was
doing more than what he did in 2024. Now
he was scoring goals and doing even more
defensive work. It flew under the radar
because of two reasons. Number one,
Madrid as a team were underperforming. I
mean, they just kept losing games. And
then number two, our expectations for
what Bellingham can achieve have been
drastically changed based on how good he
had been in his debut season. When he
plays for England, he plays in the
number 10 role and he's been fantastic.
In the 2024 Euros, he played great. All
the talk was about how bad Viní was for
Brazil that nobody noticed Bellingham
had actually shown up for his national
team. He was playing as an attacking
midfielder in a 4-2-3-1 as opposed to
Madrid's 4-4-2 diamond, but still he was
as dominant as ever. With Southgate
giving him the freedom to get forward,
he was able to score and create while
still doing what you expect from a
midfielder like tackling, tracking back,
etc. I mean, the man scored a bicycle
kick in the dying minutes of a knockout
match to keep his country alive in a
tournament, and people were acting like
he scored a tap-in or something. He was
able to perform like this because he was
playing as an attacking midfielder. He
had the freedom to go forward, and as
you can see, the more Bellingham gets
forward, the more freedom he has, the
more he's going to reward you. Now,
Ancelotti had played him as a center
attacking mid in a 4-2-3-1. Bellingham
had succeeded individually, and the team
as a whole had performed much better.
That's actually where most of his best
games have happened, like his goal and
assist against Girona, plus the
performance he put on against Valencia.
But then in the next game, Ancelotti
would put Bellingham back at left
midfield. It also doesn't help that
there's no tempo-dictating central
midfielder behind Bellingham anymore. In
2024, Jude could push forward because
Kroos was at the club. He could control
the tempo of games, recycle the ball.
He's no longer there, and there's pretty
much no other profile of midfielder at
the club that can do that role. Jude
could probably do it. Obviously not as
well as Kroos. He's not really a
tempo-dictating central midfielder, but
the problem is the deeper you play Jude
Bellingham, the more you're
underutilizing him. And because of poor
poor recruiting and lack of profiles,
you end up asking Bellingham to do 100
different things. And he's well-rounded
enough to do each of those tasks, but
he's not going to be able to do each of
them at the highest level possible. But
when you give him freedom to get
forward, and his only focus is to score
goals and create, then you get the best
version of him, the one that we saw in
2024, the one that arguably deserved the
Ballon d'Or. The truth is that
Bellingham remained and remains the
heartbeat of Real Madrid. Even if the
headlines are now about others, everyone
around the club knows his value. Anybody
who watches Madrid knows his value.
Whenever they grind out a win, you'll
find Bellingham at the center of it all,
making key interceptions, launching a
counter that leads to a goal, and having
to cover for teammates that are out of
possession. Vini and Mbappé. He has
become a leader by example in the
dressing room. He's always the first one
to go and help the guy who missed the
penalty. And in 2025, let's just say
there was a lot of missed penalties. In
terms of being a complete midfielder,
there are few better than him. Real
Madrid need to have Bellingham as the
focal point of their attack. This is a
player who should be involved in every
aspect of play, not just running around
like a chicken with his head cut off
being a work rate merchant. Whether he's
playing as a powerful number eight, or
as a number 10, or something in between,
Bellingham just keeps growing. And every
single season he's adding new layers to
his game. And Madrid fans should be very
excited because I believe his story is
only just getting started. Now, Real
Madrid's struggles go so far beyond just
Jude Bellingham. To see why this Madrid
super team hasn't worked out yet, you
got to check out this video right here.